{"tossups": [{"question": "<b><u>This Know Nothing politician left his position as Attorney General in the John</u></b> <b><u>Tyler cabinet in 1841 after Tyler refused to follow a Whig agenda. This senator</u></b> <b><u>authored a series of bills in 1860 which aimed to solve the impending (+)</u> secession crisis by reviving the Missouri Compromise and fully compensating planters who lost their (*) </b>\"fugitive slaves.\" For the points, name this Kentucky statesman and namesake of a \"Compromise\" that failed to prevent the U.S. Civil War.", "answer": "John <b><u>Crittenden</u></b> (or John Jordan <b><u>Crittenden</u></b>; accept <b><u>Crittenden</u></b> Compromise)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This archaeological site is the location of what is believed to be the oldest</u></b> <b><u>synagogue in the world, discovered by a team led by Andr\u00e9 Plassart. In order to</u></b> <b><u>properly worship the gods at this place, the graves in view from the temple were</u></b> <b><u>excavated and transported under the orders of (+)</u> Pisistratus [[pye-SIS-trah-tus]]. Thucydides [[thoo-SID-id-ees]] documented that dying was illegal on this island after the Delphic Oracle ordered the removal of all of its corpses. The Terrace of the Lions and the Stoibadeion [[stoy-BAD-ee-on]] are on, (*) </b>for the points, what Greek island that served as the treasury and namesake of a \"League\" led by Athens?", "answer": "<b><u>Delos</u></b> (accept <b><u>Delian</u></b> League)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In Essex County, this person was brought to trial after he beat indentured</u></b> <b><u>servant Jacob Goodale to death for stealing an apple. Teenager Ann Putnam claimed</u></b> <b><u>this man's wife, Martha, made a yellow bird sick with help from Satan. In an effort to</u></b> <b><u>save his (+)</u> property from seizure, this man refused to plead either guilty or not guilty after facing accusations of wizardry by Abigail Hobbs. A cry for (*) </b>\"more weight\" was supposedly said by, for the points, what 81-year old victim of the Salem Witch Trials who was crushed to death by stones?", "answer": "Giles <b><u>Corey</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b><u>This project was initially funded by the Bureau of the Census after a similar</u></b> <b><u>commercial variant of its central product was created by Northrop Aviation. This</u></b> <b><u>project's central product initially led a CBS employee to claim that it made an</u></b> <b><u>erroneous prediction after it suggested that Adlai (+)</u> Stevenson would lose in an electoral landslide to Dwight Eisenhower. This project was completed under Remington Rand after their purchase of the Eckert\u2013Mauchly Computer Corporation. Following similar projects such as (*) </b>ENIAC and BINAC, for the points, what was this project to create a line of early digital computers?", "answer": "<b><u>UNIVAC</u></b> Mark One (or <b><u>Universal Automatic Computer</u></b> Mark One)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1782, this man authorized an expedition to take Nassau from the British. This</u></b> <b><u>man's forces were victorious at the Battle of Fort Charlotte and captured Pensacola</u></b> <b><u>with the help of French ships. This man's troops captured Baton Rouge and he was</u></b> <b><u>promoted to Viceroy of (+)</u> New Spain in 1785. Due to this man's campaigns, both East and West Florida were returned to Spain in the (*) </b>Treaty of Paris. For the points, name this governor of Spanish Louisiana during the American Revolution and who lends his name to a coastal Texas city.", "answer": "Bernardo Vicente de <b><u>G\u00e1lvez</u></b> y Madrid (do not accept or prompt on \"Galveston\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Guillaume [[gee-YOM]] Cornut lost the majority of his fleet at this war's Battle</u></b> <b><u>of Malta due, in part, to the accuracy of the</u> </b><em><b><u>almogavar</u></b></em><b><u> missile soldiers. Yuan diplomat</u></b> <b><u>and Nestorian Christian Rabban Bar Sauma witnessed this war at the invitation of his</u></b> <b><u>host Charles II, King of (+)</u> Naples. That king attempted to end this conflict by challenging Peter III of Aragon to personal combat with Edward I serving as the judge of the contest. The House of Anjou lost (*) </b>control of the title Mediterranean island in, for the points, what 13th century war which began in Palermo following an incident after evening prayers?", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Sicilian Vesper</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Aragon</u></b>ese <b><u>Crusade</u></b> before \"Aragon\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A rally poster for this election year describes its candidate as \u201cthe farmer of</u></b> <b><u>north bend.\u201d A third-party candidate, James Gillespie Birney, received only 7,453 of the</u></b> <b><u>popular votes during this election year. A campaign song for another candidate in this</u></b> <b><u>election year says, (+)</u> \u201cRockabye, baby, when you awake, you will discover Tip is a fake.\u201d (*) </b>\u201cTippecanoe and Tyler too\u201d was the winning slogan in, for the points, what election year during which William Henry Harrison defeated Martin van Buren to become the ninth president of the United States?", "answer": "<b><u>1840</u></b> United States Presidential Election", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The Duke of Modena tasked this ally of Charles Louis with raising an army</u></b> <b><u>against the Papal States, only for the attack to be cancelled. All of present-day Manitoba</u></b> <b><u>was once part of a territory named after this man, who served as the first governor of</u></b> <b><u>the (+)</u> Hudson's Bay Company. In his twenties, this son of Frederick V of the Palatinate served as a cavalry commander at Edgehill and lost the Battle of Marston Moor (*) </b>during the English Civil War. For the points, name this German-English Royalist prince.", "answer": "Prince <b><u>Rupert</u></b> of the Rhine, Duke of Cumberland (accept Prince <b><u>Rupert</u></b>'s Land; or <b><u>Rupert</u></b>'s Land)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man, who was posthumously given the title \"King of Exemplary Culture,\"</u></b> <b><u>inspired Wu Zetian [[ZET-YAHN]] to name her own dynasty after this figure. Under the</u></b> <b><u>patronage of his sibling, the Emperor Wu, this figure created the classic music and</u></b> <b><u>dance style</u> </b><em><b><u>yayue</u></b></em><b><u> [[YAH-YOO-EH]]. (+)</u> This man wrote a treatise explaining how the previous ruling dynasty, the Shang [[SHAHNG]], lost the Mandate of Heaven due to decadence. The </b><em><b>I Ching</b></em><b> (*) </b>and <em>The Book of Poetry</em> were legendarily written by, for the points, what cultural hero who shares his name with an early Chinese feudal dynasty?", "answer": "<b><u>Duke</u></b> of <b><u>Zhou</u></b> (or <b><u>Dan</u></b>, Duke Wen of <b><u>Zhou</u></b>; or <b><u>Wen</u></b> of <b><u>Zhou</u></b>; accept <b><u>Zh\u014du W\u00e9n</u> </b>G\u014dng Dan; prompt on \"Zhou\" or \"Zhou Dynasty\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This system was implemented with the help of Communist politician D.N. Aidit</u></b> <b><u>[[\"EYE\"-deet]]. A \u201cunilateral action\u201d effort to enforce land reform was implemented</u></b> <b><u>under this policy, which sought to combine nationalism, religion, and communism</u></b> <b><u>together to form \"Nasakom.\" (+)</u> The implementer of this policy opposed the establishment of the Federation of Malaysia during the </b><em><b>Konfrontasi</b></em><b>. This system, lasting from 1957 to 1966, was replaced by the reactionary New Order (*) </b>of Suharto. For the points, name this political system implemented by Sukarno in Indonesia.", "answer": "<b><u>Guided Democracy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Demokrasi Terpimpin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The head of a statue of Emperor Augustus buried under the door of a temple in</u></b> <b><u>this city is now housed in the British Museum. Queen mothers of this city were known</u></b> <b><u>as kandakes [[kahn-DAH-keez]], and this city succeeded Napata as a capital. Sitting at</u></b> <b><u>the edge of (+)</u> Butana, more than 200 short, steep pyramids were used for burials of rulers in this city. The Egyptian Twenty-Fifth Dynasty (*) </b>was, at times, ruled from, for the points, what Nubian city, the last capital of Kush?", "answer": "<b><u>Mero\u00eb</u></b> [[meh-ROH-ee]] (or <b><u>Medewi</u></b>; or <b><u>Bedewi</u></b>; or <b><u>Meruwah</u></b>; prompt on \"Bagrawiyah\"; accept reasonable pronunciations)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>When this polity was created, Septimius Odaenathus [[oh-DAY-nah-thus]]</u></b> <b><u>formed an army to attack an army near the Euphrates. Aurelian captured a queen of</u></b> <b><u>this state, leading to her son, Vaballathus, assuming the role of this polity\u2019s emperor.</u></b> <b><u>Under that queen's rule, this breakaway (+)</u> state controlled much of the Levant, Egypt, and Asia Minor, but only held it for a year. Ruled by Queen Zenobia, (*) </b>for the points, what was this short-lived empire ruled from its namesake capital in Syria?", "answer": "<b><u>Palmyrene</u></b> Empire (accept <b><u>Palmyra</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This eldest son of Hedwige Liudolfing [[hed-VEE-geh loo-DOHL-fing]] was</u></b> <b><u>preceded by a king who was nicknamed \u201cthe Do-Nothing.\u201d A failed plan to deliver this</u></b> <b><u>man to Holy Roman Emperor Otto III was partly concocted by Adalberon. This husband</u></b> <b><u>of Adelaide of Aquitaine (+)</u> unsuccessfully attempted to have his future successor, Robert II, crowned co-king in the same year that this man was crowned. In order to depose Archbishop Arnulf, this ruler called the Council of Reims [[RAHMZ]]. (*) </b>Crowned in 987, for the points, which King of the Franks founded a namesake dynasty that preceded the Valois?", "answer": "<b><u>Hugh Capet</u></b> (accept <b><u>Hugues Capet</u></b>; prompt on partial answer; prompt on \"Capetian\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This ruler wrote a series of sacred hymns called</u> </b><em><b><u>jaillis</u></b></em><b><u> [[hah-EE-yees]] to</u></b> <b><u>accompany the</u> </b><em><b><u>situa</u></b></em><b><u> [[see-TOO-ah]] purification ceremony. This man established the</u></b> <b><u>Raymi festival, which greatly expanded the worship of the sun deity Inti. This ruler,</u></b> <b><u>who legendarily subjugated the (+)</u> Chanka people with stone warriors, organized his realm into four </b><em><b>suyus</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For the points, name this son of the ruler Viracocha, a <em>Sapa</em> who reorganized the Kingdom of Cuzco into the Incan Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Pachacuti</u></b> Inca Yupanqui (or <b><u>Pachakuti</u></b>q Inka Yupanki)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this war, the consuls Sempronius Gracchus and Publius Valerius Falto</u></b> <b><u>received an offer to occupy the city of Utica, which they declined. The Gallic leader</u></b> <b><u>Autaritus [[aw-TAH-rit-us]] and his fellow foreign leaders were crucified during this</u></b> <b><u>war following their loss at the Battle of the Saw. (+)</u> The prestige of the Barcid [[BAR-kid]] family increased after its leader, Hamilcar Barca, put down this revolt led by the Campanian slave Spendius. (*) </b>Rome quickly annexed Corsica and Sardinia during the chaos of, for the points, what war named for the paid soldiers who revolted against Carthage after the First Punic War?", "answer": "<b><u>Mercenary</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Truceless</u></b> War before \"paid soldiers\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man fronted an attempt to gather Swaziland militia in the mid-1970s to fill</u></b> <b><u>the ranks of Spear of the Nation. This president was criticized for ignoring anti-</u><u>Zimbabwean riots in Gauteng Province in 2008. This president, who secured his</u></b> <b><u>nation's bid to be the first African nation to host the (+)</u> World Cup, removed Deputy President Jacob Zuma from his post amid a 2005 corruption scandal. A known AIDS denialist, (*) </b>for the points, who is this second president of South Africa, an ally and successor of Nelson Mandela?", "answer": "Thabo <b><u>Mbeki</u></b> (or Thabo Mvuyelwa <b><u>Mbeki</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man died on an expedition to the Spice Islands that he captained along with</u></b> <b><u>Garc\u00eda Jofre de Loa\u00edsa [[HOH-freh deh loh-ah-EE-sah]]. This man commanded the</u></b> <em><b><u>Victoria</u></b></em><b><u> when it arrived in Seville with only seventeen other men in 1522. This man</u></b> <b><u>was promoted to lead one expedition after his predecessor was (+)</u> killed at the Battle of Mactan. This man was granted a coat of arms with the motto \"Primus circumdedisti me\" [[PRE-moos keer-koom-deh-DIS-tee meh]] (*) </b>by Emperor Charles V. For the points, name this Castilian navigator of Basque descent who completed the first circumnavigation of the Earth after the death of Ferdinand Magellan.", "answer": "Juan Sebasti\u00e1n <b><u>Elcano</u></b> (or Juan Sebasti\u00e1n <b><u>del Cano</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While serving as</u> </b><em><b><u>aedile</u></b></em><b><u> [[AY-dile]], this man charged Titus Annius Milo with</u></b> <b><u>public violence after Milo resisted an attempt to burglarize his home by this man's</u></b> <b><u>hired thugs. In an effort to get revenge against Cicero, this patrician from the</u> </b><em><b><u>gens</u> </b></em><b><u>Claudia, had himself adopted by an obscure (+)</u> </b><em><b>plebeian</b></em><b> to be elected \"Tribune of the Plebs.\" The wife of Julius Caesar Pompeia was supposed to be seduced by, (*) </b>for the points, what scandalous Roman populist who perpetrated the Bona Dea scandal by dressing as a woman to the title sacred rite?", "answer": "Publius <b><u>Clodius</u></b> Pulcher (accept Publius <b><u>Claudius</u></b> Pulcher before \"Claudia\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Prior to this event, the founders of De Beers Mining Corporation attempted a</u></b> <b><u>similar event in Rhodesia but failed. Following this event, the Kruger telegram was</u></b> <b><u>sent from Germany to congratulate Paul Kruger for defeating the (+)</u> perpetrators of this event. Although this event was ultimately a failure, as it intended to trigger an uprising among the Uitlanders [[\"outlanders\"]] in Transvaal, it was a major cause of the Second (*) </b>Boer War. For the points, name this attempted raid against the Transvaal Republic carried out by a namesake British colonial administrator.", "answer": "<b><u>Jameson</u></b> Raid (accept Leander Starr <b><u>Jameson</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>At this battle, a man serving under the alias Charles Hoffman earned a Medal of</u></b> <b><u>Honor after defeating an advance of twelve Germans with only his bayonet. Frederick</u></b> <b><u>Wise claimed that he shouted, \"Retreat? Hell, we just got here!\" at this battle after</u></b> <b><u>French soldiers requested his forces leave. (+)</u> Hill 142 was attacked during this battle, in which one side was led by Omar Bundy under the command of John Pershing. Fought during the Spring (*) </b>Offensive, for the points, what was this 1918 World War One battle in which U.S. Marines achieved victory in a forest near the Marne River?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Belleau</u></b> [[beh-LOH]] Wood", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Within these mountains, Salih ibn Mansur founded an emirate in Temsaman,</u></b> <b><u>later moving his capital to Nekor. The Jaysh, or \"Army,\" of this region was an influential</u></b> <b><u>corps of soldiers established by Mouley Ismail. The Aith Yusuf clan led a rebellion in</u></b> <b><u>this region under the command of (+)</u> Abd el-Krim, who won the Battle of Annual [[an-oo-AHL]]. French intervention and a landing at Alhucemas [[al-hoo-SEH-mahs]] turned the tide of that war in this region, which witnessed the rise of (*) </b>Francisco Franco. For the points, name this mountainous region of Morocco that rebelled against Spanish colonial rule in the 1920s.", "answer": "The <b><u>Rif</u></b> (or <b><u>Rif</u></b> Mountains; accept Republic of the <b><u>Rif</u></b>; or Tagduda n Ar<b><u>rif</u></b>; or Jumh\u016briyya ar-<b><u>R\u012bf</u></b>; prompt on \"Baetic System\" or \"Baetic Mountains\"; do not accept or prompt on \"Atlas Mountains\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Leaders of this government fought over the appointment of their deputy K\u014d no</u></b> <b><u>Moronao in the Kann\u014d incident. This government controlled the Northern Court during</u></b> <b><u>the Northern and Southern Courts Period. This government was badly weakened by</u></b> <b><u>the internal \u014cnin War, (+)</u> and it began when Takauji turned on Emperor Go-Daigo, ending the Kenmu Restoration. The collapse of this government led to the Sengoku, (*) </b>or warring states, period. For the points, name this Japanese government that ruled between the Kamakura and Tokugawa shogunates.", "answer": "<b><u>Ashikaga</u></b> shogunate (accept <b><u>Muromachi</u></b> shogunate; accept <b><u>Ashikaga</u></b> bakufu; or <b><u>Muromachi</u></b> bakufu)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Early in this war, Nito Alves was exiled and a USSR-backed coup by his close</u></b> <b><u>followers resulted in the execution of 10,000 political dissidents. Task Force Zulu</u></b> <b><u>launched the failed Operation Savannah during this conflict, stalling after losses at the</u></b> <b><u>Battle of Ebo and at \"Bridge 14.\" (+)</u> The death of UNITA leader Jonas Savimbi formally ended this two-decade conflict, during which Cuban paratroopers intervened in Operation Carlota. (*) </b>For the points, name this Southwest African civil war won by the communist MPLA.", "answer": "<b><u>Angola</u></b>n Civil War (or Guerra Civil <b><u>Angola</u></b>na)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man's best known quip occurred while Senator Joseph Bristow catalogued</u></b> <b><u>a list of the nation's needs on the Senate floor, leading this man to say, \"What this</u></b> <b><u>country needs is a really good five-cent cigar.\" This politician proposed a bill, which</u></b> <b><u>would have ended senatorial filibusters (+)</u> with a two-thirds majority, in an effort get wartime legislation passed. Edith Wilson intentionally hid the status of her husband's health to prevent this man from (*) </b>assuming presidential duties. For the points, name this Indiana Democrat and vice president under Woodrow Wilson.", "answer": "Thomas R(iley) <b><u>Marshall</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Secretary Friedrich Kritzinger attempted to resign immediately following this</u></b> <b><u>event, one aim of which was to provide more housing to ethnically German people in</u></b> <b><u>the Protectorate of Bohemia-Moravia. This summit included a protocol which targeted</u></b> <b><u>the previously (+)</u> undisturbed </b><em><b>Mischling</b></em><b>, or mixed-race people, and it was preceded by the compiling of a list of certain citizens by Adolf (*) </b>Eichmann. Reinhard Heydrich organized, for the points, what 90-minute long \"Conference\" outside of Berlin, during which the Nazi bureaucratic and military apparatus were informed of the planned \"Final Solution\" against the Jewish people?", "answer": "<b><u>Wannsee</u></b> [[VAHN-seh]] Conference (accept <b><u>Wannsee</u></b>konferenz)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A prominent figure in this group once referred to his involvement in a scandal</u></b> <b><u>as an \u201casterisk\u201d to their political career. The person that gives his name to this group</u></b> <b><u>was nominated by Ronald Reagan as Ambassador to the Bahamas. Donald Riegle,</u></b> <b><u>Dennis DeConcini, and (+)</u> Alan Cranston were members of this group, who protected a business from investigation by the Federal Home Loan Bank Board. John (*) </b>Glenn and John McCain were a part of, for the points, what group of U.S. senators that were accused in 1989 of corruption and of intervening on behalf of the namesake chairman of Lincoln Savings and Loan Association?", "answer": "<b><u>Keating Five</u></b> (prompt on \"Keating\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Governor Johan Risingh upgraded this site's defenses with earthworks after its</u></b> <b><u>settlers attacked the nearby Fort Casimir. After a ten-day siege, soldiers surrendered</u></b> <b><u>this location to the Dutch under the command of Peter (+)</u> Stuyvesant, who renamed this location Fort Altena. This settlement was built by colonists who traveled on the </b><em><b>Fogel Grip</b></em><b> and </b><em><b>Kalmar Nyckel</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For the points, name this fort located in present-day Delaware, considered the capital of New Sweden.", "answer": "Fort <b><u>Christina</u></b> (accept <b><u>Fort Altena</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"New Sweden\" or \"Delaware\" before mentioned).", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Along side the victor of this event, Mark Spitz appeared on a Sports Illustrated</u></b> <b><u>cover, but that victor of this event would not appear in another public match for two</u></b> <b><u>decades. The victor of this event criticized its format for incentivizing draws, and he</u></b> <b><u>was the pre-match favorite due to his higher (+)</u> ELO rating. An unsuccessful attempt to remove cameras from a room led to a forfeit during this event, which included the first non-Soviet (*) </b>victory in the game at the center of this event in 24 years. For the points, name this 1972 event in which Boris Spassky lost to U.S. chess phenom Bobby Fischer.", "answer": "The <b><u>Match of the Century</u></b> (accept <b><u>World Chess Championship 1972</u></b>; accept chess match between Robert James \u201cBobby\u201d <b><u>Fischer</u></b> and Boris [Vasilievich] <b><u>Spassky</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>A judge in this political family served as Alexander Hamilton's \"Second\" during</u></b> <b><u>his fatal duel with Aaron Burr, disagreeing with doctor David Hosack as concerning</u></b> <b><u>who fired first. In an effort to attract \"Copperheads,\" a member of this family was</u></b> <b><u>selected to be the running mate of former (+)</u> general George McClellan during the Election of 1864. That member of this family sponsored and named a bill whose passage came in the wake of Charles Guiteau's [[gee-TOHS]] (*) </b>assassination of James Garfield. An 1883 civil service reform act was named for a member of, for the points, which Ohio political family?", "answer": "<b><u>Pendleton</u></b> (accept George H. <b><u>Pendleton</u></b>; accept Nathanael <b><u>Pendleton</u></b>; accept <b><u>Pendleton</u></b> Civil Service Reform Act)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Wojciech [[VOH-chek]] Korfanty led an uprising in this region which</u></b> <b><u>culminated in the Battle of Annaberg against the Freikorps of the Weimar Government.</u></b> <b><u>German miners expelled from this region were relocated to the Ruhr Valley by the</u></b> <b><u>West (+)</u> German government. Frederick the Great's 1740 occupation of this region triggered the War of the Austrian Succession. (*) </b>For the points, name this historically German-speaking region of modern Poland which contains Breslau, or Wroclaw [[VRAHT-swahf]].", "answer": "<b><u>Silesia</u></b> (accept <b><u>\u015al\u0105sk</u></b>; or <b><u>Schlesien</u></b>; or <b><u>Slezsko</u></b>; or <b><u>\u015al\u014dnsk</u></b>; accept Upper <b><u>Silesia</u></b>; or Lower <b><u>Silesia</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Salem Witch trial organizer William Phips lost much of his fortune fighting this</u></b> <b><u>political entity after he abandoned a ship carrying lumber to rescue an English</u></b> <b><u>settlement along the Sheepscot River. With the repressed Acadian minority, this</u></b> <b><u>political entity fought a protracted (+)</u> guerrilla war against the British in Father Le Loutre's War. The Mik'maq [[MEEK-mak]] and Passamaquoddy [[pah-sah-mah-KWAH-dee]] are among the various Eastern (*) </b>Algonquian native tribes that make up, for the points, what \"Confederacy\" in modern day New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and Maine?", "answer": "<b><u>Wabanaki</u></b> Confederacy (or <b><u>Wabana'ki</u></b> Mawuhkacik; accept <b><u>Mik'maq</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An insult to the exalted actor Paris may have led to this man's lengthy exile in</u></b> <b><u>Egypt, as recounted by Martial. This man parodied various contemporaneous</u></b> <b><u>sycophant court officials like Crispinus [[krihs-PIE-nus]] in a tale in which officials</u></b> <b><u>argue as to how to properly (+)</u> cook a royal fish from the Emperor Domitian. This man criticized the neglectfulness of the common man with wider political and social issues through a phrase he coined, (*) </b>\"Bread and Circuses.\" For the points, name this Roman writer of the <em>Satires</em>", "answer": "<b><u>Juvenal</u></b> (accept Decimus Junius <b><u>Juvenal</u></b>is)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>While president, Theodore Roosevelt wrote a letter to this man which</u></b> <b><u>questioned the high opinion the American public had of controversial figures like</u></b> <b><u>Admiral Winfield Scott Schley [[SHLAY]]. This strategist, who opposed the annexation</u></b> <b><u>of the Philippines, was inspired by the work of Baron Jomini to develop the doctrine of</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> \"decisive battle\" at sea. Citing this theorist, Alfred von Tirpitz acquired support for the construction of a large surface fleet from Wilhelm II. The acquisition of disparate coaling (*) </b>stations was advocated by, for the points, what American naval theorist who wrote <em>The Influence of Sea Power Upon History</em>?", "answer": "Alfred Thayer <b><u>Mahan</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a painting from this series, the words \"Each According to the Dictates of His</u></b> <b><u>Own Conscience\" appear above a crowd of people who look to the left and hold their</u></b> <b><u>hands to their mouths. A woman tucks her two children into bed (+)</u> while her husband holds a newspaper upside down in a painting from this series. A man stands to raise an objection at a town council meeting in a painting in this series, which includes a painting depicting a (*) </b>woman placing a Thanksgiving turkey on a table. For the points, name this series of four Norman Rockwell paintings inspired by an FDR speech.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Four Freedoms</u></b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This order created an exception extending to December 15th which allowed for</u></b> <b><u>certain actions to be carried out with Virginia scrip. In a cartoon created in response</u></b> <b><u>to this order, a man despondently says, \u201cI have no money, and cannot get any work.\"</u></b> <b><u>Levi Woodbury (+)</u> oversaw the enactment of this order that was partly issued in response to the Indian Removal Act. Cries to \u201crescind\u201d this order were common during the (*) </b>Panic of 1837. Aiming to curb speculation, for the points, what was this executive order issued by Andrew Jackson requiring silver or gold for land purchases?", "answer": "<b><u>Specie Circular</u></b> (accept <b><u>Specie Clause</u></b>; prompt on \u201cSpecie\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 1919 propaganda poster depicts a young man patronizing one of these</u></b> <b><u>locales, claiming he is \"a member of good standing at the Poor Man's Club.\" Republican</u></b> <b><u>attorney and lobbyist Wayne Wheeler led a \"League\" (+)</u> against these specific places. In response to a weapon-wielding woman, many of these places had signs which stated \"all nations welcomed except (*) </b>Carrie.\" Prohibition led to closure of many examples of, for the points, what type of establishment which sells alcohol?", "answer": "<b><u>Saloon</u></b> (accept Anti-<b><u>Saloon</u></b> League; accept equivalents like <b><u>Tavern</u></b> or <b><u>Bar</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Senator Chuck Schumer was inspired by this speech when making a statement</u></b> <b><u>following the storming of the Capitol Building on January 6, 2021. A sentence in the</u></b> <b><u>original draft of this speech mentioned \u201ccommenced bombings\u201d in the Philippines (+)</u></b> <b>before the country was replaced in its final draft. The words \u201cworld history\u201d was changed last minute with a more famous substitution in the (*) </b>first sentence of this speech. Prompting an immediate declaration of war, for the points, what speech by President Franklin D. Roosevelt was read to Congress a day following the attack on Pearl Harbor?", "answer": "Day of <b><u>Infamy</u></b> Speech (prompt on answers similar to \u201cspeech given by FDR\u201d before mentioned; prompt on answers similar to \u201cPearl Harbor speech\u201d before mentioned; prompt on answers similar to \u201cUnited States declaration of war\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>32 war elephants were employed at this battle in which a side that included</u></b> <b><u>Stefan Lazarevic faced an assault by horse archers. The victor\u2019s son, Miran Shah, was</u></b> <b><u>in command of the right flank at this battle while the left was led by Shah Rukh.</u> </b><em><b><u>Sipahi</u> </b></em><b><u>units were utilized at this battle, which brought about an (+)</u> \"Interregnum.\" A man nicknamed \u201cthe Thunderbolt\u201d was captured at this battle fought in Central (*) </b>Anatolia in 1402. For the points, name this devastating victory for Timur over the Ottomans near what is now the Turkish capital.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Ankara</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}